[Music]
do
hello good evening and good day
everybody welcome to the 93rd live
episode of the ask a budget show
i hope you're doing well all of you and
let me see who all is there let me greet
all of you i can see umbrella
corporation
super duper abeer
deep
devyang
gala emperor
saucy
and lots of other people good evening
good day to all of you it is great to be
back
amongst you all
so let's get right into it there are a
great number of questions that you all
have asked i have picked up a bunch of
those and let's get into the questions
right away
so this is by ishan and ishaan says why
is the west so afraid of mr putin
is it primarily because he has access to
the largest nuclear arsenal in the world
or are there more reasons to it
well
mr putin represents a different kind of
he of course is a threat to the west
like you said he uh
owns the largest nuclear arsenal in the
world the russian nuclear arsenal is
larger than that of the us and they have
the technology to back it up they have
the delivery systems to back it up they
have icbms
they have nuclear submarines and they
have all kinds of other delivery
mechanisms so that is one reason for
that the other thing is that
russia controls a very large
land mass across eurasia they have
access to so many resources even if you
put sanctions on them they will be able
to remain self-sufficient they are a
very powerful nation and in and if they
ally with china then they can set up a
separate parallel
system global system they could try to
do that and that represents a threat to
essentially what
is american hegemony so for the longest
time after 1991 you had a unipolar world
there was only one superpower the us
we still have only one superpower but we
have a rising power which is china which
has a very uh significantly large
economy more than 14 15 trillion dollars
worth today
and if they uh tie up with russia that
it represents a significant threat to us
hegemony over the world
so that's one of the reasons why the
americans see
when we talk about the west we're
talking about the us
because the major power the dominant
power the hegemonic power in the west is
nothing but the us even in europe the
dominant power is the us in western
europe
so when we talk about the west we're
talking about the united states so
that's the reason why they are
you could say that they are afraid of mr
putin not because he is all powerful
today but because he could become or
russia could become under his guidance
under his
direction
a
more dangerous and a more powerful
nation in the future
and the us doctrine has always been to
never allow
another large power to rise they have
made a mistake when it comes to china
and they don't want to repeat the
mistake when it comes to russia so even
when mr putin 20 or so years ago when he
was when he expressed
a desire to join nato
so he was rebuffed and they did not
allow russia to join nato which would
have brought russia into the u.s orbit
so
they did not allow that and they kept
expanding nato eastward in breach of the
guarantee they had given
and that's how it is so they see the the
russians as a long-term threat
especially when it comes to a possible
alliance
with china and that's why
we are seeing all the geopolitical
action that we are seeing today
so that's that's the reason why
shanghajit says why didn't russia use
its best fighter jets drones or state of
the art technology like s 400 or 500 in
ukraine but allowed the ukrainians to
shoot down a number of its warplanes
helicopters tank and tanks and kill so
many soldiers
is the russian military as powerful as
we think it to be
okay so first of all uh you're saying
that the ukrainians have shot down a
large number of warplanes and
helicopters they've destroyed lots of
tanks and killed so many soldiers
so
on what basis do have you reached this
conclusion that so many so many
casualties have happened among russia's
soldiers and so many tanks planes etc
have been destroyed from where did you
obtain this data
is it the propaganda you have been
seeing on on twitter on the western
media on youtube on and on various
indian news channels
there are a couple of at least two three
news channels in india which are
reporting from ukraine they are embedded
within the ukrainian forces more or less
and they are and they are
um uh the news
that they are relaying to india
represents the western or nato
perspective of what's happening and that
see all sides indulge in propaganda i am
not making the claim that only one side
is indulging in propaganda but
when it comes to the delivery mechanisms
of information only one side controls
that
all of social media
is based in the us whatever social media
indians consume is based in the us right
all the media
is based in the u.s even these india
indian
news agencies and media
channels etc
they may have some kind of affiliation
with the us in some form or the other
which may not be directly or indirectly
visible
so
what we are seeing is nothing but
western propaganda the russians are
trying to do their own propaganda but
it's not visible anymore because it's
been cut off right
so in order to get a balanced
perspective of what's happening you have
to look at both sides of propaganda and
then you can
make your own deductions of what's
really happening
now
like i said the last time also
the best way to see
what's really happening in ukraine
is to see a big picture perspective see
the maps
and if i don't have the maps today last
time i showed the maps you could see
clearly from day one to day three to day
five to day ten you could see the
russian control over ukraine on the map
visibly represented on the map
increasing day by day so you can see the
russians are doing very well when you
look at the map that's called a top-down
approach of looking at information and
data
but if you look at a bottom-up approach
if you look at this piece of information
that piece of news and this piece of
propaganda that
is a very haphazard way of looking at
things right
so from
what i have seen personally
right and i have been keeping track of
what's happening in ukraine from day one
and before day one
so from what i have seen there have been
very few russian casualties soldiers
most likely less than two thousand
according to the media propaganda like
tens of thousands of russians have died
which is absolute nonsense
most likely there have been less than
two thousand russian soldiers who died
in a war people die
especially combatant soldiers when it
comes to warplanes helicopters tanks i
mean i have seen a couple of images
of two three tanks that have been
destroyed in whatever reason and we
don't know whether it's a ukrainian tank
or a russian tank they all have the same
equipment by the way
when it comes to helicopters etc again
how do we know what helicopter it is
they they all have the same equipment
what we do know is that within the first
two to three hours the russian russians
uh achieved complete air superiority
over ukraine which means it took out all
the ukrainian air force and the radars
all defense mechanisms
right so in the light of that you may
have some sporadic incidents of some
helicopter taken down or something but
it's not really happened on a large
scale
so it is being made to look like the
russians have suffered lots of
casualties the russian advance has been
bogged down all the various
so-called experts and think tank members
etc all across twitter and facebook and
everywhere are pouring out this
information that seems to
indicate that the russians have done a
terrible miscalculation and they are
faring terribly in the war but if you
look at the map of the advance day by
day you can see that the russians are
advancing steadily
right it's not a lightning advance it's
not a blitzkrieg like they would it
might
we would imagine a blitz great
blitzkrieg kind of advance to take
24 hours or 48 hours and take over the
whole country but blitzkrieg the name
blitzkrieg comes from the german advance
into france in the second world war and
their advance this lightning warfare
advance blitzkrieg at once was slower
than the current russian advance into
ukraine
so let's put things into perspective
right so the russians are i think uh
advancing steadily they're doing
reasonably well if you
if you disregard the propaganda to the
oppo to the opposite effect now
the question is why didn't russia use
all the fighter jets and all those
things which they do have right because
they don't they don't want to destroy
the country if they had gone
if they had taken the approach that the
americans always take whether it is
afghanistan whether it is iraq whether
it is libya or wherever or yemen or or
or the former yugoslavia the the
american approach is to go all out and
and flatten the country first nothing
should live or breathe there and then
you walk in and then you conquer the
country
that's the american way way and it
causes millions of casualties among
civilians
as we know
right i mean the so-called war on terror
has killed at least six million
civilians
right and and when when it comes to uh
the
the invasion of iraq
that uh happened in the early 2000s 2003
2004 that around that time
that killed
at least 2 million civilians in iraq do
you can you comprehend the number two
million
right
the russians don't want to do that
they have the firepower
the jets the the the machinery
the armed
armed
capability the army the military
capability to completely flatten the
country of of ukraine in 24 to 48 hours
they have desisted from doing that
they could have done an all-out attack
of the what what's known as the
so-called shock and oh approach
bring in all your heavy bombers
uh shoot
thousands of cruise missiles and other
missiles just flatten everything and
then walk in we won but that's not what
they want to do right they want to take
the country more or less intact they
just want to change
the regime they want to uh remove the
the puppet regime and install their own
perpetration they want to remove the
perpetration that's been installed by
the americans and they want to install a
pro-russia puppet regime right so it's
not about doing what's right and what's
wrong what's good and what's bad it's
all about power they want to regain
control over the country
so that's what they're doing and they
don't want to destroy the country
the best way to take a country is to
take it intact right so that's what they
are trying to do
and that's why they have not used all
the latest weapons the best fighter jets
drones and all those things they don't
want to do it they don't want to destroy
the country it's not an enemy country
they don't they don't see it as an enemy
country they see ukraine as their own
territory that has been taken away from
them so they want to take it back more
or less intact with as little damage as
possible and as few civilian casualties
as possible that is what the approach
seems to be given the pattern we have
observed over the past
few days ever since the
intervention in ukraine began
okay a couple of questions here kirtana
says
is there any possibility of india and
china entering into an agreement of some
sort especially after russia and china's
closeness will this ongoing scenario
help in
improving russia india china relations
in some way and akash says the relations
of russia and china with the west are
well known to be unsatisfactory to say
the least
russia and china have come closer in the
last few years russia and india have
always been pretty fine the us have
always supported pakistan over india
why doesn't china act smartly and make
friendly gesture towards india leaving
the crippled pakistan alone
at least till the time the supremacy of
the west can be put
to rest put down to rest well it's still
early days in the
in the current scenario
uh the ukraine invasion the russian
intervention in ukraine began
uh in in the third or fourth i think in
late february right
and we are currently in
more or less mid march
so it's still early days in the
in the conflict
and uh as we know like both of you have
pointed out correctly the chinese and
the russians
have a reasonably close relationship you
could not you could possibly construe it
to be a kind of an alliance how long
will it last is to be seen but yes they
are cooperating they are coordinating
their approaches
and there seems to be some sort of
understanding uh satisfactory
understanding between them
now the question is
is there a possibility of some kind of
rapprochement between india and china
well uh it could happen i mean it's
still early days like i say like i say
uh this this is going to be
this this could just be the start of the
conflict right if you look at the
history of let's say world war ii
uh it starts
when does it start 38 39 there's some
somewhere around that i don't remember
the exact days dates the years but you
know uh
the americans did not get involved into
the in the war for like two three years
it's only i think in 41 that the
americans got involved and the germans
had been taking country after country at
that point
so i i don't think the world at that
at that point in time even knew that
they were in the middle of a world war
right it's only later that they realized
that what we went through was the second
world war
so who knows what we are in right now
and it's still very early days you're
just two three weeks into it
as the situation evolves the chinese in
the coming year or two
may
consider it to be wise to make some kind
of agreement with india it is possible
and if it is a mutually beneficial
agreement then even india may be open to
that sort of thing and the stumbling
block is the border the border
demarcation the chinese have vehemently
refused to demarcate the border and it
is in it has they have considered it to
be uh beneficial for them to have an
undemarcated border between india and
tibet chinese occupied tibet because
that gives them the opportunity to keep
needling india and keep pressurizing
india militarily from higher ground in
tibet in order to keep india off balance
and to keep india feeling insecure all
the time because in the last 30 years
the chinese have gone way ahead of us
economically and militarily if you have
a larger economy you will have a larger
military proportionately so they see
that as a a way of keeping their
advantage uh of of driving home
constantly driving home their advantage
over india they don't want india to be
stable they don't want india to feel
secure they always want india to be to
feel constantly off balance so india
always has these problems and india will
not be able to rise uh
to the extent that it should
because they see india as the only
potential rival in asia right
but
if the things go badly in the coming
couple of years two three years then
they may find it to be beneficial for
them
to perhaps enter into some kind of
agreement or cooperate cooperation with
india it's possible
so i would say it's still early days
we have to see how things evolve the
americans are right now putting a lot of
pressure on india as well
to capitulate to give up and become a
full-fledged vassal state of the us and
to denounce what russia is doing
and just slide headlong into the nato
kind of situation and then they can take
over the whole country
in a variety of ways right through
democracy and through sub-national
diplomacy and whatever else they call it
which is essentially neocolonization so
that's what they would like to see
happen in india the americans and
india is resisting that
so let's see how things goes it is
certainly
something that could happen in the
future a kind of alliance between india
china and russia but
the
precondition for that to happen is that
india and china should demarcate the
border the final demarcation should be
done
if that happens
then uh
then there could be
an alliance or agreement between india
and china so depending on how things go
if the uh let's say russia doesn't do
well
the chinese are hoping the russians will
do well and they will support russia and
slowly they will build a parallel system
to the to the western system as an
alternative for other countries who are
tired of the western meddling and
interference in their internal affairs
whether it is asia whether it's africa
or other countries
they may even want japan or other
countries to come into that you know
possibly as if if they succeed in
constructing such a system an
alternative system
but if russia doesn't do well
in the coming
two three years then the chinese may
feel isolated
and then they may want to explore other
options so all the uh possibilities are
open right now
right so it all depends on
how this goes how the current thing goes
we are still very much in the early days
uh if the russians do well and the
americans are not able to destroy the
country thoroughly
then certain scenarios may emerge if the
russians do poorly and the
chinese feel that this supporting russia
in the long run will not work out then a
whole different set of scenarios opens
up so these possibilities are all open
right now in the next two three years
who knows what will happen we may even
end up seeing an india china alliance
the possibility is remote but it is not
zero so it could happen in the next
two two three four or five years it
could happen let's see how it goes i
cannot make a prediction because there
are too many variables that are
currently unknown but it is a
possibility
okay
says should india bring bring back
indian gold from the bank of england
seeing that the seeing the current
anti-india narrative in england i think
the figure is as as huge as 300 tons
might be a wrong figure
this is an interesting question but they
just so uh
as
from what i last remember
reading
india has more than 400 or more than 450
tons of gold
that is stored in
two banks in the west one is the bank of
england the other one the other one
is i don't remember the name of the bank
it's a bank in switzerland so there are
two banks in which india has stored
large quantities of gold the total
amount is most likely more than 450 tons
of gold and
we see it as securely
stashed away over there and i think we
must be earning some interest on it
but
like they just says is it a good idea to
bring all that gold back to repatriate
all the all the gold
from the west because
as we know
if your treasure if your assets are in
somebody else's hands
it's very likely that in
in the case the situation changes or the
relationship between the two sides
deteriorates they may
confiscate your property because it's
lying in their custody it is likely it
is possible that such a thing happen i
mean recently they have confiscated lots
of russian assets in the last couple of
weeks in the past they even confiscated
assets of other other countries i don't
remember which south american or central
american country it was but even that
was done
so if your valuable assets are in the
custody of another country it is always
a possibility that if things go up if
things go wrong
then they will confiscate it and you
will be left with nothing
so i think it may not be a bad idea at
all for india to repatriate
its gold from the bank of england and
that other bank which is in switzerland
i mean we have a large country a vast
country a subcontinent size country i am
sure we can
uh
store
this gold in various locations across
the country securely i'm sure we can do
it
we may not be
if we do that if we repatriate the gold
we will no longer be able to accrue some
interest on it but that's okay it is
better to have
what what belongs to you back in your
country then
gamble on getting a little bit of
interest and
you may end up losing everything so i
think it may not be a bad idea for india
to
in the coming days repatriate all of its
gold back to india so that's an
interesting question
dhruv kaushik says uh um yeah all right
thank you dhruv my question is that the
u.s has banned oil imports from russia
russia is offering crude oil to india at
a discounted price so should india
accept this deal and accelerate its
growth by using this cheap energy supply
in your opinion what should india do to
utilize this deal as well as not get
into the list of russia supporting
nations of the west you know what's
interesting
uh india used to buy a lot of oil
from iran
or neighboring country iran almost
neighboring country
so
when the
relationship between the americans and
the iranians went bad when it went south
the americans arm twisted india they
pressurized india into stopping
its uh
its relationship of of buying
oil from the iranians so india was no
longer
allowed by the americans
to buy oil from iran
do you understand what that means the
americans can decide
what kind of foreign policy india should
pursue
what does that tell you america has a
lot of influence in india i mean it's
all armed twisting it's all done by
force it's coercion but they have that
sort of influence in india in india when
they demand such things india has no
option but to accede to their demands
and threats right
so the americans
forced india to stop buying oil from
iran now
and and what they have also done is that
they have imposed
a whole lot of sanctions on venezuela
because venezuela is a country they
don't like and because it's a socialist
country and so on it's a country in
south america i'm sure you know right
so they had imposed sanctions on
venezuela they were preventing other
countries from buying oil from venezuela
as well now that they have blocked
russia
countries from
buying russian oil they again want to
start buying oil from venezuela right
so that is the kind of policy they have
when it suits them they will do it when
it doesn't suit them they'll do
something else but for us we have to
dance to their whims and fancies
for india right
so when they demand that we should stop
buying oil from a certain country we
have to immediately comply
but next week if they feel like again
start starting to if they feel like
buying it again from that country then
they will do it
so there is no consistency
in their behavior
right so that's what i would like to
offer to all of you first that there is
no consistency they talk about a
rules-based system there are no rules
the rules change every five minutes
it the rules change on their whims and
fancies depending on what is best for
their country but what's best for us
doesn't matter we just have to
obey their orders right that's how it is
so the question today is should india
buy
cheap crude oil from russia obviously it
is in india's interest to buy cheap oil
wherever it comes from and we have a
good relationship with russia now the
americans obviously won't like it but
the other the real question is is india
in a in a position to buy large
quantities of crude oil from russia does
india have storage facilities that's the
question uh it appears that india does
not have
large
storage
capabilities
i mean i remember reading a few years
ago like three four five years ago that
india was constructing large underground
underground caverns for storing uh
enormous quantities of crude oil you
know strategic oil reserves i'm not sure
how far that has progressed but it
appears that as of today india doesn't
have
the kind of capacity we should have
in order to be able to benefit from such
a windfall that a country offers us
very cheap crude oil i am not sure if
india has the capability the capacity to
store large quantities of such oil so in
case we have some leftover space in
which we can store crude oil it may not
be a bad idea to buy cheap crude oil
from russia
of course the americans won't like it
and india may have to face
some repercussions from for doing that
so yeah it's it's a
it's a question that india should
consider
uh seriously
but it is also we have to consider the
pros and cons first of all do we have
the capacity to store a large quantity
of
cheap crude oil if it comes in do we
have the capacity secondly if we do have
the capacity if we do have the storage
capacity
then is it a good idea
to risk
the wrath of the us
if we buy the the russian oil because
the americans are already very
very kind of kind of furious with india
because india has
not
bent its knee to american demand this
time when it comes to voting against
russia in the u.n security council
resolutions india has refused to vote
against russia so there is this
tsunami of blowback that's coming on
india
privately publicly publicly on social
media in other places as well and there
must be diplomatic
repercussions also and other things also
so if india goes ahead and does one more
thing like this and buys crude oil then
we could face some
bigger
repercussions from the u.s maybe
sanctions of some kind who knows
anything is possible they're already
talking about sanctions uh the cat
sanctions ca a tsa sanctions because
india has bought the russian s 400
missile defense system
so the americans are not happy about
that also they may they are still
considering
they're still threatening that they may
impose the katsa sanctions on india so
we have to see how that goes so they are
already pressurizing us they are already
threatening us
and if we do this then there could the
threat could really materialize
so uh the thing is when it comes to the
u.s
there's always a threat on your head
they are the global hegemon they are the
guy with the biggest stick and the stick
is always ready to fall on your head if
you don't behave and if you don't dance
to their whims and fancies
so that's where we are
so
it is obviously a good thing for india
if we have the storage capability this
is a storage capacity to buy cheap crude
oil from russia but what are the
consequences of doing that that is what
india needs to consider if it has if we
have the extra storage capacity
okay akash says i am learning uh data
science and artificial intelligence from
iit madras my question is this
inexorable technology is bound to enter
every nook and corner of modern
industries can isro and drdo also
benefit from this uh as i would be glad
to put my mind in developing national
strength instead of increasing profits
of u.s based mega corporations how
crucial can this be in the near future i
mean a very good question
uh data science and artificial
intelligence machine learning all of
that is crucial in today's world uh it
has military applications it has
non-military applications it has
geopolitical applications it's all about
controlling the world and infiltrating
the minds of people and so much more i
mean with data science you in artificial
intelligence machine learning you can do
things like targeted advertising
targeted propaganda i do advanced image
recognition facial recognition speech
recognition you can do war gaming you
can do predictive analytics you can do
forecasting of all kinds of things you
can
indulge in biowarfare you can create new
kinds of bio agents
you can discover new kinds of bio bio
agents using data science machine
learning artificial intelligence you can
do psychological profiling of people
based on their public social media
profile their aggregators aggregated
social media
behavior and trends and patterns then
you can indulge in cyber wolf warfare
you can create intelligent autonomous
weapons systems combined with robotics
that can be a game changer you can do
target recognition combat simulation
combat training threat monitoring
situation or
situational awareness in the battle
space domain and creating an integrated
battle space when it comes to a warfare
on a uh in a real-time manner so there
is so much you can do with data science
artificial intelligence intelligence
machine learning neural networks all of
those things the question is is india
pursuing these things or not we have
isro we have drdo we have uh
hal and all these other
organizations
are they agile enough
are they pursuing these technologies we
also have quantum computing which is a
very important uh
technology a very important and
interesting frontier of science that is
currently under development is india
pursuing that
uh
in case india is pursuing all these
things
then yeah it is it is uh
it would be great to have intelligent
young people
uh joining
the effort
in building up these technologies
developing these technologies for
india's benefit the easy solution is to
migrate to the west
and work as a
as a glorified cyber to build
uh
to build the platforms for the west
which they will use eventually in the
long run against all other countries
right
so in the 1960s and 1970s lots of
indians
especially from kerala etc they went to
the gulf countries and they exchanged
their time for a little bit of money and
they built up what is now all the
glittering cities of dubai abu dhabi all
that
those were fishing villages it is indian
labor
and indian talent
that constructed all these cities but
who owns the cities it is the arabs
owned the cities and what indians got in
return was a little bit of money which
they sent back to
their families in in kerala etc right so
the same thing is now happening
in the cyber domain
indians
want to be middle class want to become
want to live comfortable middle class
lives so they will be they are willing
to exchange their time for a little bit
of money and create all of this
priceless intellectual property for the
west
so what india needs to do is give
indians the opportunity to do the same
for india
i mean we need the private sector to to
contribute in this and the government
also can contribute in this
so
drdo is an organization that could
really uh contribute a lot to that but
unfortunately drdo is very antiquated it
is ossified the kind of system they have
is
it it
the kind of structure that drdo has it's
it's very bureaucratic very very
stratified it belongs in the 1960s i
mean you you
they have i don't know 25 000 employees
or so maybe 30 000 employees and only 5
000 of these employees
at most are scientists so the majority
more than 20 000 employees are
non-scientific personnel
and all the money that goes into drdo
most of it is utilized in the salaries
in all the other benefits that these
non-scientific personnel get so the
majority of the money that goes into
drdo is used for non-scientific work so
these organizations they need reforms
they can be radically reformed and made
more agile made more um
driven
and in that if you can do that then they
they could really contribute they could
really transform the country
so i hope that happens and the thing is
this these technologies they're going to
like like akash says they're going to
enter every nook and cranny of the
modern world they're going to penetrate
your daily lives to an extent that you
will not even realize so we need to
also uh
we need to ensure that india needs to
ensure it doesn't get left behind
uh
so it's so the answer is it's really
crucial that india develops these
technologies the government needs to
push this the private sector needs to
get involved
and if that happens it will be great for
for
young people in india people who want to
contribute to the country they will be
able to use
whatever whatever
skills they learn whatever knowledge
they acquire
in in the course of their studies and
they'll be able to use all this
knowledge and and these skills
for the benefit of the country so it is
crucial that india develops these
technologies india gets involved in this
and i hope that people like akash young
people like akash and many others like
him
will get the opportunity to use their
talents for the benefit of india instead
of
building up the
intellectual capital for the west
okay um
what do you think about india's fighter
attack jet making technological
capabilities at present
we all know the horrible time overrun in
developing the tejas but do you think
india has learned her lessons from the
pages ordeal and applied these those
lessons in pages mark ii
amca
advanced medium combat aircraft and the
twin engine deck based fighter
also don't you think it would be
beneficial to have a large number of one
or two types of planes let's say 400
pages instead of a lot of small numbers
of different planes wouldn't it make
maintenance and production cost
difficult if you have if you have to
maintain large numbers of different
kinds of planes very good question
so uh yes we know that the pages program
the lca pages program was delayed
horribly for like
it began in the early 1980s
right the development of the plane and
the the the
plane was given it's the the fighter
plane was given its
final operational clearance only in the
2010s i'm not sure how many years ago it
happened maybe five six years ago at
most right so the entire process
it took more than 30 years to develop a
basic
fighter plane a light combat aircraft
and the reason for this is not because
our scientists are incompetent
it's because our politicians did not
want this program to succeed
these politicians who were controlling
the country
they were getting large amounts of i'm
see i'm not saying all politicians are
we're doing this but
i'm sure
some were
so what happened is that the
specifications
of the fighter jet were repeatedly
changed when they were about to to be uh
to to mature so when the development
when you issue a certain set of
specifications you want the length to be
this much the width to be that much the
wing wing span should be these many
meters
the weight should be maximum this and so
on so forth when you have a set of
specifications the the engineers can
build a plane based on that but at the
last minute when the plane is going to
be finalized when you change the
specifications you do start the
development from scratch again
and if this happens repeatedly then your
your program will be delayed by decades
and this is not only something that's
happened with the tejas it also happened
with the h.a.l marut a brilliant plane
that was trashed by by the indian
government it was a brilliant fighter
plane from the 1960s the h.o.l maruth
firstly what they did was they gave it
an underpowered jet engine so it was
never able to to perform to its full
potential and secondly they did not
allow
the plane the design to be developed
further and to be made more mature and
give rise to a mark ii version or or
more
uh
versions or more further iterations of
the plane so india could have had a
whole family of fighter planes based on
the hl maruth today but we just uh
shut down the program
then we started the
lcds program in the in the 1980s and
it's only in the last four five six
years that the
the mark one version
uh has been given its final operational
clearance i don't remember exactly which
date it was look it up i don't have the
i don't have all the data stored in my
memory but it's reasonably recent
now what we have is a well function is a
very good aircraft it's a light aircraft
it's a small aircraft but it functions
very well
it's it's a very high quality aircraft
don't listen to what some experts tell
you
all right there are certain experts who
say it's a terrible plane it's garbage
please don't listen to them please don't
all right everybody has some motivations
and some agendas i'm not taking any
names but there are some people who say
that forget about them
the fact is that the lca lc8s mark 1 is
an exceptionally good aircraft it's not
an exceptionally good aircraft it's a
very good aircraft
all right
and
that serves as the foundation
for future aircraft which will be
which will have
modifications and enhancements which
will give them
a far better a better advantage than the
what what so those will be will be
more evolved aircraft so the pages mark
two
is going to be a different kind of
aircraft it's going to be slightly
larger than the than the mark one plane
and it's going to have a number of
improvements a lot of improvements over
the mark one
uh version of the aircraft then you have
the amca the advanced medium combat
aircraft
which will take all the lessons
which our scientists and engineers
learned during the process of making the
lca pages mark one and they will not
have to reinvent the wheel from scratch
they will take all of
everything they learned
and they're going to be able to to to
have this
new aircraft flying within a decade or
so right and the same goes for the twin
engine deck based fighter so once you
have the experience of developing a high
quality
flying platform or fighter from scratch
then you don't have to keep reinventing
the wheel every time you design a new
aircraft you already have what works you
know what works you know what doesn't
work you have
learned through painful trial and trial
and error what works what doesn't work
so you can immediately apply it
in the design and development of the new
aircraft so every time you make a newer
iteration in your aircraft you learn
more and more and it becomes easier and
easier for you
to build better aircraft so i think
india has learned all the the lessons
from the pages ordeal and they will be
applied they are already being applied
in
the the design and creation of the
new aircraft there are other aircraft
also which are being which are being
developed there is
yeah let's not go there all right so
that's what's happening india has
learned the lessons we are developing a
number of aircraft
now the other question is will it not be
beneficial to have a large number of one
or two types of planes instead of small
numbers of lots of different kinds of
planes so today we have a number of
mig-21s a number of mig-29s
we have the sukhoi 30s
we have jaguars
and uh in the past we had all we have we
have the rafales as well
and
we have the lca pages mark one then the
mark two will come in
so we have a large number
of different models of aircraft right
so it makes
it complicates things
you will need to acquire lots of
different spare parts from lots of
different suppliers you will have all
kinds of different assembly lines and
you will have mechanics who will have to
specialize in one kind of aircraft and
things like that so it complicates
things instead of doing that if you have
300 sukhoi 30s 400 kgs aircraft mark
minecraft and 400 they just mark two
aircraft let's say just three types of
planes and eventually in the future 10
years down the line you will have
let's say 300 amcas and 200 twin engine
deck based fighters so if you have large
numbers
of aircraft but only two three models it
simplifies things yes so it it
it is beneficial to do it that way
especially if you are
building your own aircraft in your own
country if you don't have a foreign
supplier it makes it it makes things
even easier so in the next 10 20 years
india is going to indigenize everything
and india is going to build its own
fighter aircraft there will be a fourth
generation aircraft hopefully a fifth
generation aircraft as well and a twin
engine deck based fighter for the for
the aircraft carriers and all that all
that
so it makes maintenance
easier if you're building your aircraft
yourself you know if you have fewer
aircraft models so yes what you're
saying is absolutely absolutely right so
that's the direction in which india
needs to go india needs to stop buying
planes aircraft and other military
equipment from other countries and try
to develop its own indigenous
arms industry that will be the best way
to go forward in the long run
and it is going to be the thing that is
the best for india's national interest
sudan says i read that india is planning
to outperform china in the solar panel
and semiconductor shortage crisis what
other avenues can india explore to
increase our influence and importance
for other countries even further
especially is there something we can
provide to russia that can potentially
save them from becoming a chinese
satellite
so
india is not planning to outperform
country x or countrywide india is
planning to become a major power
when it comes to solar panel technology
solar energy
altogether
and in
in the semiconductor industry because
right now as
i think everyone would know there is a
semiconductor shortage crisis which was
precipitated by the whole kowid
pandemic so semiconductors these
microchips etc they are everywhere they
are required everywhere from automobiles
from from from cars to washing machines
to computers to everything
and if there's a shortage of that
prices go up things
these appliances and these devices their
availability becomes reduced and so on
so it's a big problem
so india
this government the current government
has realized how crucial
semiconductor the how crucial the
semiconductor industry is and the chip
manufacturing industry is for the
national security of the country
so india is planning to
india is in the process of setting up
this industry in india on a large scale
and hopefully in the next decade in the
next 10 years india will become a major
semiconductor
and microchip
etc
power in the world you know the industry
should take off hopefully in the next 10
years that is the plan that has been
designed and it is being implemented
right now and also when it comes to
solar panels and the solar industry
because india has this enormous
surface of solar uh
of solar power so that all the sun that
we get india is a very sunny country we
can utilize it
to
generate solar power and that that is
obviously a green thing to do right
uh climates and all that so yeah that's
what india is doing now what other
avenues can india explore to increase
our influence and importance for the
other countries even further india needs
to become a manufacturing powerhouse
it's as simple as that manufacturing all
kinds of things and if you manufacture
things your technological prowess also
improves you become more advanced
technologically
and that's good for the country
so the thing is when you manufacture all
kinds of devices and all kinds of
commodities yourself in house in your
own country
you don't need to import those things
from abroad that way your economy grows
you save on foreign exchange you don't
have to
send money to others to get their their
commodities you are able to uh
manufacture everything yourself and if
you manufacture if your manufacturing
industry is good enough then you can
even export
those commodities to other countries if
you are manufacturing things that they
need
and that
grows your economy so that's what the
chinese used in the past 30 years to
become an economic giant
now
as we know the world is trying to look
for options other than china the world
is trying to decouple china to some
extent because they uh understand they
realize that this is uh
creating a monster to some extent so
india could offer an alternative if
india gets its
gets its house in order
yeah so the best way to increa to
increase
our influence and importance and our
stature
uh economically and globally etc
is to become a manufacturing powerhouse
a manufacturing superpower that's what
india needs to do if you look at the
history of the world countries that
manufacture
and countries that that export more than
they import they inevitably become
uh major economies and that's what
happened to india
historically always india was always an
expo a net exporter
always of various goods and commodities
throughout its history and that's why
india was always the largest economy in
recorded history until the in the last
500 600 700 years right so that's what
india needs to do india needs to find
ways of becoming a manufacturing
powerhouse a manufacturing superpower
everything needs to be manufactured
in-house we need to stop importing
things we need to start becoming an
exporter of all kinds of things that's
what india needs to do how to do it the
government needs to figure out we have
experts in at all levels sitting there
they need to figure out how to do this
it's a challenge for sure it's a
challenge but we need to do it somehow
or the other so that's what needs to
happen is there something we can provide
to russia that can potentially save them
from becoming a chinese satellite see
right now india has to look out for its
own interest uh
if india rises if india becomes a
manufacturing power then maybe we can
help russia in some way but our first
priority has to be india
everybody's first priority is their own
national interest in the past for
decades india and russia were close
allies cooperating together but it is
only because the our india our national
interests converged
india was looking out for its own
national interest in whatever way it was
doing it and the russians were looking
out for their own national interest and
because the two converged that's why
there was this cooperation and you could
call it an alliance of some kind
so india needs to look out for itself
first we our our job is not to help
other countries that are in need our job
is first and foremost to help ourselves
and to ensure that our people
in our country
will be guaranteed long-term security
and prosperity that's what we have to
worry about we our job is not
to
help other countries in need
that is not our job it is the job of
every country to look out for their own
best interests and that's what india
needs to do
shazam says the recent government
restrictions on ngos please explain how
will it change india's geopolitical
scenario in the coming years
um i am not quite sure of what exactly
the details are of various restrictions
on ngos i think there will be some fcra
restrictions etc fcra is the foreign
currency regulation act
and the thing is this
okay let's look into what a ngo is
what's an ngo
ngo stands for non-governmental
organization
which means that it is an organization
that is not in any way linked to the
government or any government and it
usually ngo typically works in
in in the field of social welfare
uplifting society and doing things like
that
so that's what an ngo is now
what you will find in india
is that there are more ngos in india
than schools and hospitals put together
isn't that strange
so in the ngo industry seems to be
booming
in india i mean it was booming in the
past
i mean about 10 years ago you had more
ngos in india than schools and
hospitals put together
so why
is was this industry so lucrative
ngos are supposed to supposed to be uh
mostly non-profit things right and yet
if you look at
take any ngo at random which is doing
reasonably well and you will find that
their employees have very high salaries
and where does the money come from and
these are the questions that you
typically obviously arise right and ngos
are allowed to ge to obtain funds from
abroad through the fcra act all that
and the thing is that
if you if you trace back
the kind of
funding that some ngos receive you will
find that they are linked to very
dubious organizations from abroad
many of these organizations that are
funding indian ngos have links to
foreign governments
all right so this term ngo
non-governmental organization
even though it's technically a ngo it
many of these ngos are
basically nothing more than than
agents of foreign governments
and
what we find that there are lots of ngos
that go to the indian judiciary uh start
these they they
file pils public interest litigations
that are taken seriously by the
judiciary and they are able
to influence public policy in india
so
ngos indian ngos there are more or less
puppets
of certain foreign powers and forces
are dictating
and influencing public policy and govern
government policy
inside india
so these ngos have become
a means
of exerting foreign interference in
india's internal affairs
whether it comes to
government policy public policy the kind
of rules that are enforced in india
whether it comes to religious
conversions or whatever else
you will find that all of this is
happening through ngos via ngos so the
term ngo is a misnomer
these
ngos may not be related to the or linked
to the indian government but many of
them
are extensions
of foreign interests and they are acting
on behalf of foreign governments mostly
it is western governments there are some
governments in the middle east some some
some organizations
in some eastern countries maybe some may
be linked to china also who knows i
don't have the specific details but this
is how it's done
so there is this massive
ngo industry in india it's very
lucrative they get lots of funding from
abroad
their employees are typically very rich
not all but
some of them have very
prosperous employees who get the
salaries in terms of lacks of rupees per
month some of them do yeah
and they all
not all but many of them act as conduits
of foreign governments and foreign
influences within india
so this is a huge
national security threat for india
right the thing is if you crack down on
ngos
then certain foreign powers
will say that democracy is under threat
in india
they will lower your democracy ranking
in india and when you go to that country
their head of state or their vice head
of state will give our prime minister
lectures about democracy
public lectures things like that
so you see there are multiple ways in
which very powerful countries
can
interfere
blatantly in the internal affairs of
india
all right when it comes to these
so-called protests that happen every
every winter season in north india
if you trace back the funding see no
protest can happen without money no
extended protest that goes on for two
three weeks months
can ever happen without a significant
amount of funding
and logistics it's not just funding you
need a whole lot of logistics to to to
sustain a protest for a long period of
time
and where does all this expertise come
from it comes from ngos certain ngos i
would imagine
which are linked to certain foreign
governments
so that's how
there is
this foreign interference that's
happening in india's internal affairs
so that is the reason why the government
will have its eyes on the ngos i i heard
recently that there was
some restrictions that were made that
were placed on certain ngos
the thing is
uh that is problematic
because if you place
too many restrictions then these foreign
powers they will complain and they will
uh
they will say that india is sliding down
under the in the democratic in the
democracy index india is no longer a
democracy it's an autocracy it's a
fascist nation it is a dictatorship i
mean this is what the western media
keeps saying day in and day out and the
moment you do this there will be more of
that happening
so
so if india is
placing some restrictions on ngos it
will be because of this only now i would
wish
that there should be a law that is
passed in india that no ngo is allowed
to operate if it
if it receives funds from abroad
right that's how it should be
there should also be a law that says no
political party should be allowed to
receive funds from abroad because all of
that is nothing but
interference foreign interference in
india's internal affairs
as of today india is most likely not in
a position to pass such a law because of
pressure from from outside countries
so that's where we are today so
that is a bit a little about
the
restrictions on ngos and what ngos how
are and what they actually
represent
i am a swiss-born indian whenever i am
at an airport the airport security
sometimes mistreats me until i show them
a swiss passport raising the tantalizing
question of why indian people need a
visa to and go through all these
difficulties whereas people from other
countries like argentina
or mexico who are much poorer enjoy visa
free access to the eu and even some to
the us
you know there's a word for this it's
called racism
it's all about skin color
argentina is a christian country most of
the people are of europe european origin
most of the people who are visible are
of european origin their natives have
been mostly wiped out when it comes to
mexico mexico is a brown country they
look like indians you go to the u.s if
you're indian people will mistake you
for a mexican very often but mexico
again is a christian country it's under
the u.s umbrella so that's why things
are better for the mexicans if they
travel to europe etc but for other brown
people from the middle east from india
etc there are all kinds of restrictions
so let's understand how these
restrictions started
a hundred years ago or 150 years ago
there were no restrictions there was no
requirement to carry a visa or a
passport or anything you could just
travel right in the old days the system
of passports and visas did not exist
when mohandas gandhi went to the uk and
from there he went to south africa he
did not care he did not have to apply
for a visa to go to all these places he
traveled through various other countries
as well while going there there was no
requirement of a visa
so how did all this start how did these
borders become so uh so inviolable and
how did
this system of uh having to apply for a
visa before you were able to go
to a country how did all this emerge so
what happened is that in the last 500
years
the christian countries the western
countries the european countries
they colonized
most of the civilized world they
destroyed the local culture civilization
and they plundered and stole all the
wealth there is they reduced all of
these countries all of these cultures
and civilizations to destitution
especially india they stole all the
wealth and all of the wealth of the east
end of africa as well was transferred
into the hands of a small percentage of
the world's population the white skinned
people the europeans and their colonies
in the u.s in north america south
america etc so these are the people who
now
held
the vast majority of the world's wealth
now if you allow
people to travel
unrestricted then you will find that
people who have been made very poor will
want to now travel to the countries
where the wealth resides so that they
can enjoy the better living standards so
to prevent that from happening all these
restrictions were put in place and
because it was the black-skinned people
of africa and the brown-skinned people
of
asia mostly india who had been
whose countries had been destroyed and
whose wealth had been stolen so the
majority the strongest restrictions were
placed on these people
on indians
around africans
so today you find
that there is this discrimination
if an indian wants to go to the u.s if
an indian store wants to go to the eu or
whatever they have to fill up a long
visa form and wait for i don't know how
long it is a week a month whatever for
their uh to go to the embassy they have
to stand in queue they have to answer a
questionnaire or interview or whatever
and there's a whole number of documents
you to provide to them just to prove
that you are
worthy of coming to the great country
but when they come to india when
americans or europeans come to india
they they complain about the visa
process oh it's so tedious and we have
we were made to uh fill up this form and
things like that
we are accustomed to walking into a
country and not needing a visa
so they have these double standards when
it comes to indians they want to have
they want to put all kinds of
restrictions in place but when they come
to india they want to have visa free
access to the country and when they
don't get it they complain
the crib about it right
so there is the there is a concept of
reciprocity right which india doesn't
follow actually
we give too many benefits to these
people while we don't get those benefits
so this is all nothing but racism
uh it all depends to a large extent on
the color of your skin if you are born
in europe
you will know that racism has always
been latent in europe it's always been
like
kind of below the surface but nowadays
in times of war it's all come out into
the open it's very ugly
racism i mean we beli we in india
believe that uh
europe is a very progressive place there
is no racism there is equality
egalitarianism very liberal place
very liberal countries especially the
western european countries that is not
quite the case my friends
if you live in those countries you will
see that there is a latent racism always
below the surface you are always treated
a little differently depending on the
color of your skin
and that's how how it has always been so
i'm not surprised that you are a
swiss-born person and yet you face all
these problems with airport security i
am sure elsewhere too
so this is what's known as racism it's a
it's a mostly a european
thing it is they who have invented this
other countries are not racist yeah
not to that extent at least
not to that
extent the way the europeans are racist
you will find russians are not racist
you will not see racism among russians
which is strange i mean
let me give you an example
when the indian prime minister
goes to washington see his body language
is it comfortable or is it kind of
not very comfortable
now see the indian prime minister's body
language when he goes through to the
middle east when he meets the head of
state of the uae or saudi arabia
see the body language it's way more
relaxed and comfortable see the indian
prime minister's body language when he
meets the president of russia vladimir
putin
it's very relaxed very comfortable but
when the indian prime minister goes to
let's say washington and meets the u.s
president the body language is
much more
tense
so you can see you know i mean these are
very subtle things but you can observe
that so there is a very uh
there is a difference
in the the way indians are treated in
certain countries especially in the in
what we know as the west compared to
other countries
so that's just how it is
okay uh since kennedy offered nuclear
technology in 1961 to india before the
chinese invasion and neheru refused it
after the war but after the war why did
they change their stance and oppose our
nuclear program
it's believed that they were behind the
death of homie baba and tried measures
to shut down india's nuclear program my
question is why did the did they change
their stance
so it is indeed true that u.s president
john f kennedy had offered nuclear
weapons technology to india
in the early 1960s before the chinese
invasion of india
he had offered to help india
create build and detonate a nuclear
weapon the if india had agreed to this
if india had accepted the u.s offer
india would have been the first asian
nuclear weapons power
mr nehru
the great mr nero refused the offer
and
as a result the chinese became the first
asian nuclear power if india had nuclear
weapons in 1962 the chinese may not
would probably not have dared
to try and invade india right
so the americans wanted india to be the
first asian nuclear weapons power the
americans wanted india to be an american
ally
mr nehru rejected the american offer
in his great wisdom he was a
magnificently
wise man so he
in his
uh as as a consequence of the great
wisdom that he had he rejected the offer
and then what we saw is that he
steered india
into an alliance
with the ussr india essentially became a
satellite state of the ussr i know some
people don't like me saying it deal with
it india became a satellite state of the
ussr over time
right so the americans wanted
india to be an ally of the us maybe a
satellite state a client state of the us
but what they saw is that india
under mr narrow very rapidly became a
client state or a satellite state of the
ussr so essentially india went into the
enemy camp
the cold war was already on
early 1960s you had the cuban missile
crisis right the cold war was very much
on it was threatening to become a hot
war and india had taken
unambiguously the side of the ussr and
rejected the offer of the us
so india
declared itself the signals that india
gave to the us was we are aligned with
your enemies so that's very simple
that's why they change their stance
right
initially the americans also wanted
india to become one of the five
permanent members of the of the u.n
security council the offer was made to
india twice the second time the offer
was made to india was in conjunction
with the russians the russians and
americans both offered india a place on
the u.n security council a permanent
place and mr narrow again in his great
wisdom he rejected that so after seeing
all of these
rejections the americans said there's no
point dealing with india and the
congress regime under mr nero and
whoever else and that's why they quickly
changed the stance and
from then on you saw that the americans
they they started cultivating pakistan
and eventually they even cultivated the
chinese
from the 19 mid 1960s onwards so that's
how it went the reason why they changed
the stance is very simple it's because
india rejected their offer
and became instead of that an ally of
the ussr now some of you will say no no
no what are you talking about you are
stupid
india was not aligned
so how can you say india was an ally of
the us we had declared we had said many
times we are not allied arabi do you
understand the difference between
actions and words
non-alignment was words
but every action that india took
was that of an ally and a satellite
state of the ussr
please understand the difference between
actions and words all right so that is
why the americans very rapidly change
their stance and then the
relationship between india and the us
became quite adversarial
swarup says stephen tibbetts co-founder
and chief executive of ziva
a tacoma washington based firm
has designed a prototype of a flying
sorcerer-like vehicle which recently had
a successful full-scale vertical takeoff
even the uae has been working on such
vehicles for public transport for since
a few years
so do you think such kind of air travel
will be the future of traveling in the
distant future no
no no no it will not be the future
of traveling
on a large scale in the distant future
what these companies are creating is
they are creating expensive toys for
rich people
so when you have a helicopter kind of
thing or a hovercraft kind of thing or
something that that looks like a ufo
it's gonna be something that everybody
desires but only rich people can afford
it cannot be something that can be used
for mass transportation
even the biggest planes that we have
today the boeing 747s and the airbus
400s a400 or whatever they
can be afforded mostly only by the rich
people of the world
right
i mean the common man and woman in india
would rarely travel by air
right
maybe once a year maybe once in two
three years
if if at all
so
even regular air transport is at least
for countries like india kind of
something of a luxury to some extent
it's the things are changing now even
common people can afford
to travel by air things are changing but
until very recently it was kind of a
luxury
now these vehicles that these people are
creating flying social like things these
are going to be really expensive things
what you need
is mass transportation mass
transportation means
large vehicles like trains that can
transport
a thousand two thousand people at one
time
and that are inexpensive and that are
available
on demand
i mean let's say you want to go let's
say you are living in bangalore or
chennai and you wake up tomorrow morning
and you have this
this urge
to go to let's say guwahati
and let's say then okay you go to the
station you buy a ticket and two hours
later you're on a train and you can go
there so if that sort of situation is
accessible to you that is mass
transportation that is the mass
transportation
transportation that is available and
accessible
when it comes to a flying saucer-like
vehicle it's going to cost a lot of
money only few a few people will be able
to afford it and it's not going to be a
solution for mass transportation it's
gonna be a one-seater or two-seater or
maybe four-seater or maybe 20-seater and
it's going to be really expensive so it
is not going to be the future of air
travel these are just expensive toys
the future of air trans
the future of traveling transportation
in the in the long run
in my opinion most likely will be
ground-based travel maybe high-speed
railways
maybe
underground railway systems or whatever
but something that that can carry lots
of people large numbers of people at
speed at scale and bring them from point
a to point b in a reasonably short
amount of time
so all these fancy vehicles yeah this is
nothing but
toys for rich people so that's how i see
it
urchid says we all know our gdp most
more than 33 percent of the world's gdp
at least maybe more
but what about our per capita gdp do you
think that was a boastful number too
given how this land has always had a
huge population
interesting question so
uh india see if you look at the uh
statistics the data that angus madison
the economist
put forth
uh you will see that according to his
calculations projections which is the
gold standard
in
the economic history of the world
according to his calculations india
always had a gdp of at least one third
of the world's gdp
until the 1700s at which time our gdp
dropped very precipitously because of
the british destruction of india's
economy and the country now india's
population if you look at the population
of history of india
india's population was typically
when the british left india
undivided india had a population of
approximately
between 300 and 350 million which is if
it was 300 million it is one-fourth of
what india's population is today
right
and if you look at the large-scale
history of india so let's go back a few
thousand years
if we go back about to around 3000 bc
or 3500 bc we had the sindhu
civilization suppressing the phase of
india civilization the saraswati hindu
phase of india's civilization with the
which the western people call the indus
valley civilization or the harappan
civilization which is nothing but one
phase of india's civilization so if you
go back to that time india was
demonstrably
demonstrably the most technologically
advanced culture in the world a fully
industrialized fully urbanized
civilization with the highest technology
available at the time anywhere in the
world
and at that time i can guarantee that
india's gdp would have exceeded half the
world's gdp
and at that time
it is calculated it is estimated
that india's population
was around 5 million
5 million
not
300 million not 1.4 billion
which we are reaching today it was
merely 5 million
so more than half the world gdp for 5
million people can you imagine the per
capita gdp which we would have had
so uh we have to put things in
perspective this is a very interesting
question i mean i wish that people would
think more along these lines
so we have to look at what the
population was like from the best
estimates that historians and scholars
have so the best estimate
for india's population
uh during the saraswati sindhu phase was
about 5 million people
and india's gdp was
more than 50 percent of the world's gdp
for sure maybe two thirds of the world's
gdp because that's how advanced india
was
so the per capita gdp would have been
ridiculously high more than any other
country even today
so these are not boastful numbers the
numbers are
actually under representations of what
india would actually be india's gdp
would actually be because even if you
look at the data that angus medicine has
put forth there are all there are a
number of
assumptions and oversimplifications that
are not quite accurate when it comes to
india so even the data for the last two
thousand years which says that india was
about one third of the world's gdp is
kind of an
under representation what of what in it
actually would have been
even in the last 2000 years the actual
data the actual gdp of india would have
been closer to i would say 40 to 45
of the actual of the entire world gdp
most likely more likely
so that's what i can offer but in the
past
before
080 or 0 bc whatever you call it
india's economy was even more advanced
and
the per capita gdp would have been
really really high
and again by archit
there are always claims that education
in ancient india was great but very
limited to certain sections of the
society leaving a great a large part
uneducated what's your take on other on
that
do you think that might be true i don't
necessarily see that as bad or even if
true
china still does this which
and and so on and so forth just curious
how you think india dealt with ancient
india dealt with education so there are
claims
with certain sections of uh india's in
historians and researchers they make
these claims that india was a very uh
in egalitarian society unequal society
you had this caste system in india by
caste system castism brahminical society
brahminical patriarchy brahminical
dominism domination and the evil
brahminical religion which only gave
education to the brahmins and maybe the
chatris and everybody else was it was
denied education even women were treated
horribly in india because india is a
terrifyingly patriarchal society
right so that's what these people claim
and that's what we are taught in our
education system we are taught all of
these things as if they were facts but
on what bases do they make these claims
if you make a claim it has to be on the
basis of data of information
where is this data
on what basis of the claimed that it's
in so and so a period of time we had
these problems that india did not deny
education to large parts of society and
denied education to girls and women
where is the data that supports this
claim did they pull this data out of
thin air or somewhere else
there is no data that supports these
claims that people these people make the
only data that is available about not
ancient india but more recent india
is the data that is available in this uh
this book the beautiful tree by drampal
and he
meticulously and painstakingly collected
all the data
that the british themselves had
documented
so before the british destroyed india's
education system they spent several
decades collecting data
about the kind of education system india
had what what were what kind of
education was imparted what was the
demographics that was included in that
and so on and so forth so and so forth
so according to the data that the
british themselves collected before the
destroying the india's education system
everybody got an education the so-called
high castes the so-called low-cost
everybody got education in this temple
schools
so the the place
so india was a land of temple temples
until recently today we have other
things that are cropping up temples no
more new temples are coming up now in
india but india has for thousands of
years been a land of temples every city
every village every
every street corner had a temple
and temples were not just places of
worship these were centers of education
so in small temples there is a saying in
tamil that don't go and live in a
village where there is no temple
right
this is not a secular saying this is a
hindu saying isn't it
so
so what you see is that what what was
there is that these temples there were
these were centers of education
that's where all the local kids would go
in the local temple to get to gain their
basic education so what what they were
taught was they were taught sanskrit
they were taught the mother tongue and
they were taught basic mathematics and
whatever else right uh
whatever the other basic topics were
taught so the
main basic things
basic education
and if you were good in in studies and
you wanted to pursue a higher education
you would go to one of the great temples
so great temples were not everywhere but
in every uh
you could say district kind of area you
would have one great temple
so you would go there to receive a
higher education and if you wanted to uh
to receive an even higher education you
would go to one of the mahaviharas or
one of the great universities like
nalanda takashira and so on so forth so
that's how the system was india was the
most educated land in the world the most
educated culture in the world
right so according to the statistics the
british collected in which the rampara
has presented everybody got an education
the so-called high caste the so-called
low castes boys girls everybody got an
education go buy the book and read it
all right so that's the only data we
have
and and the other data which is like uh
data that comes from foreigners is uh
uh what the the accounts of people like
shwanzang and fahia etc the chinese
pilgrims and monks used to come to india
to acquire education because india was
the home of education right so they used
to they they would come to india to to
acquire knowledge wisdom education and
they also observed that everybody was
educated right you even had female monks
and all that even in the vedic times you
had female rishikas
many of the verses of the rig veda
itself the oldest
literary text in human history
many of the verses of the rigveda have
been composed by females by ladies
the rigveda is the holiest book
in what we now call hinduism
show me any other religious book
in which a significant portion of the
text has been composed by women
so all of these claims
that these so-called scholars and
historians make these are outright lies
and fabrications so fabrications show me
the bases on which they make these
claims these are merely opinions
and what they do is this one person puts
forth an opinion without any basis
without any factual basis then 15 other
people
and this person puts forth the opinion
in the form of a
of a paper a research paper that
research paper is published in some
journal
even though there is no factual basis to
the claim but they publish it anyway
then 15 other so-called scholars will
cite that paper
that research paper and write new
articles which all uh make the same
claim again repeat the same claim so now
we have 15 or 16 papers which make the
same false claim then lots of other
people will cite those 15 papers and
they will create a citation ring around
that and so many papers will now after a
few years be there which all make the
claim and they cite each other so they
give references to each other but it all
starts with one false claim
and that's how these narratives are
constructed in in academia
so academia is rotten whether it is the
west whether it is in india whether it's
anywhere else academia is rotten the
entire academic academic system in the
world today is built upon the
foundations of the western system the
western colonial system that was
introduced in india in the 19th century
we still follow the same system today in
the 21st century the same old master's
degree in english literature and all
that nonsense which people have to go
through
so
these are all lies and fabrications
please don't believe them because there
is no factual basis to these claims
okay muhammad danish khan says what do
you think india would be like today if
it had not if it had not been colonized
would it be a single country or multiple
kingdoms well what india would be
whether it would be a single political
unit or multiple
multiple units india would still be a
single civilization
today india no longer has the status of
a civilization let me explain why
a civilization has certain
characteristics it is characterized by
high levels of education high levels of
prosperity high living standards a
single unifying civilization language
and a single unifying culture which may
manifest itself in various forms
so single unifying civilization language
and
all of its institutions
should be based in its own indigenous
culture
if we look at india
we have a unifying language today which
is english i am forced to speak to you
in english right
we have
institutions and laws
which are based in western values in and
western principles and western morality
india's constitution is western and
origin it is not indian in origin
right
it is not based on indian values on
indian cultural and civilizational
values
india's institutions whether it is the
parliament
whether it is the judiciary
they are all
based
on western institutions
india's laws
are not based in indian values so india
is a thoroughly colonized country and
once you have
this kind of situation you are no longer
a civilization so india officially
ceased to be a civilization in 1944 or
1947 until 1947 india was a struggling
civilization but in 47 the death
of the civilization was announced when
india
accepted british dominion status and in
50 or 51 or whatever whichever year it
was we adopted this ridiculous
constitution undemocratically
and since then we have no longer been a
civilization we have been a colonized
western
of a colonized
nation state west valley nation state
so if india had not been colonized
whether it was whether if india today
was a single political entity like the
mauryan empire the koshan empire
whatever or whether it was a
loose coalition of various kingdoms
india would still be
a single civilization so that is what we
have lost due to colonization and today
we are becoming even more rootless all
of our values are our western values all
the entertainment we watch is rooted in
foreign culture
uh the education system is making us
more rootless and this is the
situation we are in right now if it
persists like this for another hundred
years
everything that is left of indian
culture will be gone
so that's where we are today but i am
still hopeful that things may turn
around
so india may have been today a single
country a single kingdom you could say
or empire whatever or maybe a bunch of
multiple kingdoms whatever but it would
have still be still being a single
indigenous civilization which we no
longer are today
so that's an interesting question uh
danish asked
vishal says gotham buddha was called
shakyamuni the sage of the shakyas my
question is were the shaktiyas and the
suckers of the skittions the same was
gotham but the kitten that's an
interesting question so even i used to
believe you know 10 years ago or so that
the structures and the suckers of the
shakkars were the same it may not be the
case
so so who were the sketchy the the the
suckers or the shakkas
these were
indian origin nomadic people
so in the old days in the days of the
veda in the puranas in the vedic age
there was this there were multiple waves
of migration out of india to the west to
the north and the west
and the people who migrated out of india
went and settled down in persia
to the west of persia and all across
central asia
and after a few years after a few
decades maybe a couple of centuries they
kind of
gave up some of the values and some of
the traditions of india so they no
longer followed the vedic lifestyle
properly
so that's why they were given the the
name of lectures
but they were still indian origin people
the entirety of central asia was indian
origin you still find ruined stupas and
ruined temples all across central asia
everywhere
you even find
ruins of hindu temples
in
georgia armenia and places like that in
the caucasus region and there must be
many more so the whole of central asia
was
indic was indian
and you had this nomadic people who were
of indian origin
we know what they looked like based on
their dna analysis they had light brown
skin brown eyes and dark hair
and they were reasonably tall so these
are these were known as the skittions
these keithians ruled the central asian
steppe region right they were nomads and
they were very powerful warriors but
they did not stay in one place at one
for long they were nomads
uh so these were the skittions and
eventually about two thousand years ago
they reintroduced themselves into india
they conquered parts of northern and
western india and they assimilated very
harmoniously within the indian
population because they essentially were
the same people the same culture there
was no significant difference between
indians and schizoids genetically or
culturally
so the assimilation was very harmonious
and you had many great kitchen kings in
western india
rudra daman rudra
i figured out forget all the names but
you had this great mahakshatrapas
especially in western india in gujarat
subrashta etc they controlled india's
great ports that did all the trade with
rome et cetera egypt and so on so these
were the skittions in those kitchens and
the central asians kitchens the same
people one could also consider the
kushans
to be the easternmost ketians
so these guys the skittions entered
re-entered india about
2200 or so years before today
approximately
now gotham buddha
according to conventional historiography
according to the conventional
chronograph chronology of india of
india's history
he lived about 200 two and a half
thousand years before today around 500
bc thereabouts
that's what
the official consensus is so if he lived
in 500 bc approximately
that would predate
the time of the skittion
reintroduction into india by about three
centuries
right because during the mauryan era or
before the mauryan dynasty before the
before the mauryas you had the nanda
dynasty right
during the time of the nanda dynasty
there was no
uh significant intrusion of keithians
into india
none whatsoever almost right and so
therefore it is uh unlikely
that gautam buddha siddhartha gautam the
prince of the shakya people would have
been as kitten so maybe it's just a
coincidence that you had a clan of
people or a community of people
chatriers warriors who were called the
the shakya people and whose and to whom
got them but they belonged so most
likely i i would say that the shakias of
northern india present day nepal and
bihar etc
most likely they were not sketians
right so that's what i can conclude
based on the chronology and all of this
historical background so most likely
gautam buddha was not as ketian he was a
northern indian chatria from a princely
uh from an aristocratic royal family
okay akash says why was albert einstein
so adamant on the cosmological constant
that the universe is static and later he
had to delete it from his field
equations what does it say about the
scientific community's temperament
against the inflow of new and
exceptional ideas
one more example could be that of
avilube who says
umuamua could be an extraterrestrial
object but he was completely sidelined
uh p.s it would be great if you could
call away to a podcast he is a great
speaker
explains complex ideas beautifully okay
interesting thank you for the
recommendation let's see if i can
do that so the question is about the uh
cosmological constant so what is this
cosmological question so in 1915 albert
einstein published
his general theory of relativity in 1905
he published the special theory in 1915
he published the general theory of
relativity
in the general theory of relativity you
have the very important equation called
the field equation of general relativity
which relates the mass energy
mass and energy with gravity and it
replace the older
law of gravitation which is newton's law
of gravitation so what you have
according to the einstein field equation
is that the curvature of space-time is
intricately related to the amount of
matter and energy that is passing
through that uh that region of space
time right so that's the einstein field
equation if you want to understand what
the equation is it says r mu nu minus
one half r
g mu nu is equal to eight pi eight pi g
po
above c upon c raise to four times t
mu nu so that is the uh field equation
it's not a single equation it's a set of
ten equations
looks very simple it's a system of 10
partial differential equation
equations which relate the mass and
energy to the curvature of space time
right so this
set of equations it matches newton's law
of gravitation for weak gravitational
fields
now what we find so what albert einstein
did is that he uh
he what he did was he approximated the
universe as having a constant density in
all directions so if you look at the
universe it has mass in some places it
is empty in some places but if you zoom
out
to very large scales then you find that
it has you could
approximate it as having a constant mass
energy density in all directions so
einstein did that approximation and he
was able to solve the equations for a
simplified
toy universe with constant density
everywhere
and what he found is that the uni the
equations the solutions they give you
something
they will either cause the universe to
contract or expand
right
so that's what his equations were
telling him
that the universe will either contract
or expand but in those days in 1950s in
1915 in the in maybe in 1920 the data
the information that we had
was that the universe was static it was
unchanging it was neither expanding nor
contracting those days the only
knowledge we had was that of the milky
way galaxy
and we thought scientists in those days
thought that the milky way was the
entire universe right so that was the
scientific consensus that's what the
best observations showed now in the
1920s edwin hubble an american
astronomer
he uh
took he uh
he
observed
that the milky way was just one galaxy
there were lots of galaxies beyond the
milky way
and he also discovered
that these galaxies
beyond the milky way were all getting
more and more distant from us they were
all receding from us in all directions
which indicates
that the universe is not static
it is expanding
right
so before this information was available
einstein realized that he feel this he
his field equations they would make the
universe
expand our contact or so what he did was
he introduced an in
additional term
which is which is the cosmological
constant and what this constant does
is to is that in order to counteract the
contraction of the universe it produces
a net outward force it's like a
repulsive gravity kind of force to
balance out the contraction of the
universe right so that's what it did
and later on when he when it was
discovered that the universe is actually
expanding then he realized that my field
equations were telling me this all the
time and i i inserted this equation
which should which with this this term
in the equation
which
may not have been necessary so he called
the cosmological constant that he
inserted into the field equations his
greatest blunder right so that's what he
did it is denoted by the by the greek
term lambda now in the late 1980s or
late 1990s it was discovered that the
universe is not just expanding
but the expansion of the universe is
accelerating the universe is expanding
faster and faster the expansion is
accelerating
and this term the cosmological constant
that had been deleted
from the field equations now had to be
reintroduced because it
because it represents
in
an anti-gravity kind of force a negative
gravity kind of force that causes the
expansion of the universe so einstein's
greatest blunder actually
was valid
right and that's what we nowadays
consider to be dark energy
so nobody forced albert einstein to
delete
the cosmological constant from his field
equations he did that himself
because it was discovered new data came
into
was was
new data
was made available
and based on the new data he realized
that there was no need for it
but after his death
in the late 90s it it was again realized
with the introduction of of even more
data that yes we need such a term in the
einstein field equations because the
universe is expanding and the
expansion is accelerating
so that is the story in brief in rough
about the
cosmological constant
now when it comes to the scientific
community the temperament against like
akash says inflow of new and exceptional
ideas it's always been there
whether it is the scientists whether it
is any other community there's always
this resistance towards new ideas nobody
likes new ideas for instance we have
they had this stranglehold of the string
theory mafia in theoretical physics for
many decades if you look at the us
most of the funding in physics in
theoretical physics goes into string
theory
so if you want to have a career
in theoretical physic physics in the us
you need to be in string theory these
days it's been like that for a very long
time nowadays there are
questions have been raised about and all
so it's always been like that
so there is always this group think
mentality there is always this
thinking by consensus
and uh
that's always been there so and that's
one of the reasons why there is no new
there's been no new real breakthrough in
theoretical physics since 1980
since uh
since the theory of inflation was
introduced by
alan guth
there was 1980 or 81 after that there
has been no new genuine breakthrough
theoretical breakthrough that is
supported by
uh
experimental observational evidence
since 1980 or 81.
so
theoretical physics has hit a brick wall
because of this group think mentality
because of the temperament against the
inflow of new and exceptional ideas
and like you say uh avilube
said that um could be an
extraterrestrial object and the entire
scientific community condemned that
why
it is certainly possible it could be an
extraterrestrial alien
object
but
so there was a very
very strong backlash against this theory
which is perplexing that's not how you
you're supposed to behave as a scientist
so you have all these problems in
science today
akash again says what is the definition
of life according to science i read
there is no consensus on it death is
defined as irreversible succession of
all functions of the brain my question
is what keeps us alive and what dies
when someone dies
because according to the bhagavad-gita
it's the divine soul that allows the
functioning of the incentive matter
which we call body and even for layman
it sounds extremely common sensical
maybe even except maybe for militant
atheists
okay
there is no signifi there is no
one definition of life according to
science if you look at it from the
perspective of neuroscience
there is a certain definition if you
look at it from the perspective of
biochemistry there is a certain
definition if you look at it from the
perspective of physics
of thermodynamics there is a different
perspective a different definition
so the mainstream definition of life is
more bio biochemical
in nature
life is uh seen as a biochemical process
which itself is problematic because the
biochemistry can stop for some time and
if it is see for instance
there have been instances
of people
who went into a coma or went into a
shock kind of state
their heart stops
and their heart doesn't beat for like
15-20 minutes
and then they are successfully revived
by shocking their heart or whatever and
then they are brought back to life
so if the definition is a biochemical
definition which would indicate the the
the heart would stop and various
biochemical processes would stop then
the person would have died would have
been considered to be dead
and then when the heart restarts after
20 minutes
and the consciousness comes back
does it mean that the person came back
from death
which is not quite true right
so there are problems in all the various
definitions of life and the reason for
that is that life is not a substance it
is it is a
process what exactly the process is we
don't quite know
we don't quite know we don't understand
the body we don't understand
the body well at all
if you uh there is this guy very famous
guy what's his name you are noah harari
he says
he says that the human body is nothing
but a
hackable machine
the human body is
it's an animal that can be hacked there
is no such thing as the spirit or the
soul it's all just just a set of systems
that can be hacked that's what he says
so i don't agree with this sort of
definition the human body is not a
machine with a set of systems that are
interconnected
lots of scientists have such uh
perspectives lots of scientists have
very different perspectives but but
those perspectives now become mainstream
see in the west today you have this
commercialization there is this
reduction of the human being to a
commodity
you are just one uh
you are some
you are simply part of the big market
and they want to commodify everything
even the
uh
even the pharmaceutical industry is
commodified even healthcare is
commodified so they want to hack human
beings
they want to reduce human beings mere
numbers and
and commodities
and in that system
uh
the idea of the spirit and the soul is
very problematic because then
you have to treat human beings and all
life differently not just as numbers and
commodities
the problem is that from the from the
perspective of science there is no
definition of life there is no
definition of soul there is no
definition of spirit so now when we talk
about the bhagavad-gita we are no longer
talking about science
so we have to understand this very
correct very
very uh carefully
that science is about i have said this
many times let me repeat it
science
is about physical
uh
what is science about
science about is about physical objects
and
observable and measurable phenomena
spheres spirituality
is about
non-physical objects also in non-physics
non-observable phenomena also so when
you talk about the soul in the spirit we
are no longer talking about science
we're talking about either philosophy or
spirituality right
so from the perspective of science there
is no definition of soul or spirit
because a soul or a spirit cannot be
observed it cannot be measured
right
so uh
so you have scientists who say that the
human emotions are nothing but chemical
reactions
i don't agree with that
it's as if we understand everything and
that's all it is we don't understand the
brain we don't understand the mind we
don't understand the body we don't
understand our genes
more than
of the genome is not understood at all
and they call it the dark matter of the
genome
and yet people are trying to hack the g
the human genome and they do all the
genetic engineering they don't even
understand what could happen what could
be the consequences you understand less
than two percent of the human genome but
you want to start hacking around
so that is the kind of approach that we
have today without understanding things
we want to start modifying things right
so the truth is we understand almost
next to nothing about our genome
we understand next to nothing about our
neuro chemistry about the human brain
about the human mind
we don't know what consciousness is we
don't have a definition of consciousness
is consciousness
an emergent phenomenon that emerges out
of the complexity of our of our brain
or is it something else altogether we
don't know we don't have the answer
we don't even have a proper definition
of life i mean viruses
according to various definitions of life
viruses
are half living half dead
they do have dna they do reproduce
but they have some characteristics that
are more consistent with the properties
of crystals
and non-living objects than
living objects so this is a complex
field
life
doesn't have a clear definition
the consciousness itself which does
exist we know it exists
so it is something that does exist it is
not
an unmeasurable phenomenon it is an
observable phenomenon but we don't quite
have a definition of that
and maybe the consciousness is what is
connected to what is known in philosophy
and spirituality and religion
as the soul or the spirit
so we don't quite know our understanding
of science is very rudimentary it is
very limited there are plenty of
scientists who like to prevent who like
to pretend like we like science can
explain everything
science cannot explain lots of things it
doesn't mean that science is wrong it
means that our level of intelligence
is able to perceive only a certain
amount of science and the and that our
understanding of science is very limited
it doesn't mean science is wrong
maybe in the future science will be able
to deal with
things like consciousness
and other such things as well so that's
what i can say
i don't know what keeps us alive what
dies when someone dies we no but no
scientist has the answer
uh our ancients our philosophers our
our great gurus rishis etc did have did
have the answers
those answers can be found in our
scriptures in our openness in the vedas
in the bhagavad-gita etc
but that cannot be
brought
into the realm of science because it is
not science the vedas the bhagavad-gita
these are spiritual and philosophical
texts
civilizational and cultural texts these
are not scientific texts
so science
is very limited in its scope and science
cannot explain what life and death are
what the spirit is what the soul is if
it does exist and what consciousness is
which does exist
so these are the the significant
limitations that science
uh is constrained by
okay sanatorium says the chinese were
and are still a high level society they
have diversities in their food entire
culture and even variations in the
school of thought and philosophy
confucianism and taoism etc
they relatively opt for an ideal
peaceful life so why did they adopt
communism midway does it aid the chinese
government to reach their goals faster
i see communism as creating tension
among its people and the reason for that
aggressiveness please shed some light
please understand this
the chinese people did not decide one
day to hold an election and decide that
yes based on the result of the election
we will all adopt communism now that's
not what happened
it is the chinese communist party that
won the chinese civil war
it defeated the kuomintang
it took control of the country by force
and imposed communism
which was its
ideology on the people of china
nobody was given a choice whether
whether you accept or not everybody had
to accept it because they had the power
of the gun
what did mahathong say he said political
power flows from the barrel of a gun
so communism was imposed top down on the
chinese people by the chinese communist
party after the chinese communist
party's victory in the chinese civil war
when they defeated the komintan to
komentang and exiled them to the island
of formosa now known as taiwan
so the chinese people did not adopt
anything they were made to swallow
communism wholesale by force
by the chinese communist party that is
what happened
all right and today the chinese the
today china is no longer a communist
country
china is an imperial system today
the chinese president mr xi jinping is
essentially the emperor of china
and they no longer have this communist
model of collective
property collective wealth
and all of that
china is a capitalist society today an
out and out capitalist society and yet a
very controlled economy
and all the power
resides in the hands of the chinese
communist party so it is no longer a
communist country it is an imperial
system it is a proper imperial system
they have reverted to the system they
have always followed for the last two
and a half thousand years
that's what china is today so they went
through us through a phase of communism
under mao zedong after mao zedong died
with the uh ascent of then shopping
in china
the system was transformed they slowly
moved to a state-controlled capitalist
system
so that's what we see today
and they uh
they tried to uh
copy the singapore system to a large
extent the system that was implemented
by
lee kuan yew in singapore which
completely transformed singapore in just
a couple of decades
so that's
what happened in china china is not a
communist country anymore and the
chinese people had no say
in
what happened there it was something
that the chinese communist party imposed
on the country
all right
dengar singh johann says i sometimes
think there is no meaning to my life
because i don't know about the very next
moment of my life no matter what i
become or game in gain in my life but
one day i'll be gone none of these
things will ever have any impact on me
after i'm gone i don't even know whether
individually individuality will exist or
not i can't focus on my studies nor do i
find any aim of my life before because i
am foreseeing
that there is no meaning to this
material world then i naturally tend to
move towards spirituality so do you get
such thoughts how do you deal with it
interesting uh question by dhonga singh
johan
so what you are describing is known in
some quarters as nihilism that life has
no meaning existence has no meaning
what's the point of doing whatever we do
what's the point of existence
i have never personally gone through
that phase
um
and you so the thing is this um
there is no meaning to the material
world all that i can't the thing is this
see
every single person in the history of
the of humanity
has died
right so death
is inevitable
but that doesn't mean that we have to
think about death all the time
just as we are born one day we die
that's how it is
and nobody is exempt from that uh
from from that
so one day everybody is going to be gone
but it doesn't mean that our life our
existence
whatever however long it lasts is
meaningless
right
the thing the trick is to find meaning
the trick is to find your own purpose in
life everybody has a certain purpose
and how do you find your purpose in life
it's by
looking inward first of all trying to
understand who you really are truly deep
inside
see every person is unique every person
has a
unique personality and character
i know for a fact
that i am today at this age the same
person exact same person i was when i
was two years old
i have acquired a whole lot of knowledge
i have acquired a whole lot of
behavioral traits
i am wiser with the years
i've acquired certain
maybe behavioral traits and all that
certain attitudes but who i am deep
inside
is still the same as what i was when i
was two years old there's been no change
really
so we are all
something unique and whatever is
intrinsic to us never changes throughout
our life
and to find our purpose in life
we have to first look inward and and
find out who we really are
and the problem with most people all of
us mostly is that we never get the time
to spend alone with ourselves and to
introspect we are always
interacting or consuming things
consuming information consuming
entertainment music whatever
and the problem with today's
entertainment is it
imposes
this
attitude or this mindset of nihilism on
all of us recently very recently a
couple of weeks ago less than a week ago
i went and watched this hollywood movie
batman the latest batman movie
my goodness how depressing that movie
was
dark nihilistic
they are glorifying
depression their glorifying mental
illness
they are showing that relationships have
no meaning the world has no meaning your
life has no meaning even if you may love
somebody you should not be with them
that sort of thing
so that's what hollywood is glorifying
today and the more we consume this this
sort of entertainment the more we're
gonna feel that way
right
the truth is that life
is beautiful life can be beautiful life
should be beautiful life can be and
should be meaningful but you will not
find your meaning and purpose in life
unless you spend some time alone with
yourself and try to understand who you
really are and the best way to spend a
useful meaningful life
and to be happy
is to
help others and serve society in some
form in some way
that if you do that if you spend all
your time in doing something in creating
something good or contributing something
good to society
in a way that makes you happy deep
inside then you will not find that your
life has been meaningless when the time
comes to go
right so you have to first find what
makes you happy everybody has something
that makes them happy
and that is the meaning that you seek in
life that is the meaning you need to
find in life
so everybody needs to do that especially
when you're young when you're young
you're confused when you when you're
young you are clueless i have been there
when you are 18 years old when you're 15
years old when you're 20 years old you
are clueless you may think you know lots
of things but you are clueless
everybody goes to that phase
and sometimes you're lost sometimes you
don't know what is the meaning in life
sometimes you have this enormous
pressure of society
right
do study study for 20 years
study study study study 10 hours a day
12 hours a day you're not allowed to
play sports you're not allowed to do
anything interesting you're forced to
study for hours and hours
so you don't find anything good in life
you don't find anything fulfilling in
life and once you're done with your
studies you have to go and get a job and
then you are under the pressure of the
job and your bosses and your co-workers
will
have all this influence on you so you
never find anything fulfilling in life
that's the problem that everybody goes
through today that's the kind of society
that we have created in india today look
at the back breaking burden that we are
placing on little kids
school and after you're done with school
homework and expectations
exams year after year after year no
wonder there is so much depression among
kids today
right
so what we need to do
my dear friends is to find some time to
step back
breathe
spend some time alone discover who you
really are discover the spark of
divinity inside yourself
find what really makes you happy and
pursue that you will have pressures from
society you will have pressures from
family from your co-workers and all that
but you have the strength to rise above
that also discover the source of that
strength
and the thing is yes we're all gonna die
but if you spend a life that is useful
to others if you help others if you make
others happy if you contribute something
good to society then when the time comes
to go
you will have left the world a better
place than than what it was when you
came came into it
so i don't think life is meaningless
i think life is beautiful i think life
is is meaningful if you can help others
serve others create something of value
that others can benefit from if you do
that
you will you will live a meaningful life
and when the time comes you'll say okay
time's up
move on so that's what i would say i
would say be cheerful be positive
and find your purpose in life
find what makes you truly happy not
momentary pleasure
momentary pleasure can be acquired
through drugs through alcohol and what
not
but once that
temporary high goes away you will feel
worse than when you started off
what you seek is what makes you happy
gradually and over time the happiness
increases
not temporary ups and downs that is not
happiness that is just mere chemical
pleasure it's hitting the dopamine
center of your brain that's not what you
want you want something that really
makes you happy in the long run and
constant happiness so that's what you
need to discover for yourself everybody
is different what makes each individual
happy is different but if you can
discover what that is if you can find
what fulfills you and what makes you
truly happy in the long run you will
have found the purpose of your life and
then your life will be spent doing
something meaningful
and good
that is what i can say my dear friend so
don garcin johan i hope
you do that
and please be positive please please be
optimistic life can be great life is is
good and life is great
you just have to find your own path in
it
all right my friends it's almost two
hours now thank you very much for all
the questions very interesting questions
i had to i could only take a few
so let's keep doing this and i look
forward to many more sessions like this
with you all thank you very much
and i will see you very soon again bye